Red Square
a place of power and piety and at its
heart a museum with secrets dark and
strange.
A terrible Ivan.
A revolutionary Rolls-Royce.
Napoleon's most shameful dishonor.
And the lost art of winning a lethal
game.
Secrets hidden in plain sight.
Inside Moscow's [music] State Historical
Museum.
>> [music]
>> From the Stone Age to the modern day
the State Historical [music] Museum of
Moscow tells the story of Russia and her
people.
The 19th century gallery is filled with
artifacts that speak of wealth,
nobility, and sudden death.
This is the museum's collection of
dueling pistols.
It's one of the largest of its kind in
the world
and is never seen by the public.
>> [music]
>> The pistols are ornate almost works of
art.
That's because they were made only for a
select few.
In 19th century Russia, pistol duels
were the preferred method of settling
disputes among the noble class.
By 1715,
dueling had become so popular it was
killing off many members of Russian
aristocracy.
The Tsar outlawed the practice,
declaring it foolish.
But not all duelists were fools.
The brilliant writer and poet Alexander
Pushkin is considered to be the father
of Russian literature.
But in his own time, Pushkin was
notorious for fighting duels.
A nobleman with a sharp tongue, he was
often challenged by other nobles who
claimed he had offended their honor.
>> [music]
[snorts]
>> Okay, this is our pistol.
Military historian Andrey Shilbakh has
brought a replica of the type of dueling
pistol that Pushkin would have used.
Now we start loading it.
We make sure that the powder is compact
enough. We are ready to shoot, but
first don't forget to put
>> Of course, the best way to survive a
duel is not to fight one.
But in a society where honor was
paramount, that wasn't always an option.
A nobleman's honor was in the greatest
danger at social occasions.
Fancy dress balls were rife with sexual
tension,
often instigated by men, but sometimes
the flames of jealousy were fanned by
women.
Pushkin's wife, Natalia, was a notorious
flirt.
At a public function, he caught her
enjoying the attention of a handsome
French officer, Georges Dantes.
Hurt and enraged, Pushkin challenged
Dantes to a duel.
Back at the gun range, Alexei is making
slow progress. And the recoil would be
quite strong.
Determined to channel Pushkin's cool,
Alexei collects his nerves and steadies
his hand.
Andrei has brought along an opponent for
Alexei.
Champion marksman, Alexander Lebedev.
Alexei
>> Like the duelist of Pushkin's era,
Alexei and Alexander will face each
other in a secluded area.
But for the purposes of our
demonstration, they will not fire lead
balls at each other. Instead, they are
each equipped with a modern air gun that
shoots a single paintball.
In accordance with 19th century rules,
the opponents will begin 20 paces apart.
At five paces, there is a line that
neither man is allowed to cross.
Lowering a handkerchief will signal the
beginning of the duel.
The duelists then have a choice.
They can take their shot immediately
or wait until they move closer to their
opponent.
When Pushkin dueled with Dantes, he was
filled with rage. He charged the line
hoping to score a kill shot at close
range.
But his anger-fueled plan failed.
Dantes fired first, [music] scoring a
direct hit to Pushkin's midsection.
On the modern gun range, Alexey and
Alexander take their positions.
Are you wounded?
Help. Help.
As Pushkin lay wounded, he struggled to
take his shot.
D'Anthes did the honorable thing by
standing still while Pushkin fired.
He received only a flesh wound.
Two days later,
Pushkin would die of his injuries.
The greatest writer in Russia
killed because he lost his cool in his
29th duel.
>> [music]
>> In Moscow's State Historical Museum, one
can stroll back through time
all the way to the Stone Age.
Here in a gallery dedicated to Russia's
earliest inhabitants, there is something
haunting and strange.
>> The skeletons of a boy and a girl that
were buried head-to-head
in a single grave.
Their remains were unearthed not far
from Moscow
where they had laid undisturbed for over
20,000 years.
Both children were covered with beads
that numbered in the thousands.
Why they were buried this way and why
they died so young
is a museum secret.
Our investigation begins in the town of
Zaraisk, 160 km south of Moscow
in the region [music] where the children
lived their brief lives.
In the shadow of a 500-year-old castle,
there is a 23,000-year-old
Stone Age settlement.
Here, archaeologist Sergey Lyev leads a
team that has uncovered a wealth of
evidence about how early humans lived
and died.
In prehistoric times, they were
>> [music]
>> hunting.
It was a perfect view on a valley and
they can see
animals
walking there. And the site is rich very
much in artifacts.
Very, very many. Now, the collection is
coming to 1 million pieces.
Along with flint tools and knives, the
team has discovered a fertility goddess
and a talisman of the natural world.
>> [music]
>> We see the most impressive object is
here.
It is the bison figurine. From the other
[music] side, there is a traces of red
ochre symbolizing blood.
And we think [music] it is a real magic
ritual linked with hunting.
The bison is carved [music] from the
same material as the beads from the
children's grave.
Ivory from the tusk of a woolly mammoth.
During the Stone Age, woolly mammoths
were by far the biggest game, as heavy
as a bus with tusks 5 m long.
In the museum, above the children's
bones, a panorama depicts the long-held
theory that hunters killed mammoths by
driving [music] them into giant pits.
Sergei believes the illustration is out
of step with recent discoveries.
From modern point of view, it looks a
little bit fantastic because first, if
it is permafrost, it is quite hard to
dig in it. And
you can imagine the size of mammoth and
what size of pit it should be. So, maybe
after 1 year of work,
they will succeed, but how they will put
mammoth inside?
So, summary,
this theory doesn't work.
Sergei has found evidence that the pits
were actually dwellings, roofed with
mammoth bones and hides.
It means that it was very, very, very
much important in their life. They used
them for constructions, they used them
for producing tools, and probably for
food.
The latest research suggests that
mammoths were brought down with spears.
In the treeless tundra, some spears were
made from mammoth tusks that were
straightened over a flame.
Such spears were found in the children's
grave.
This could mean that the children took
part in a hunt
and were killed by misadventure,
crushed or gored by a wounded beast.
If so, their bones may tell the story.
Recently, at Moscow's Archaeological
Forensic Laboratory, [music]
Dr. Maria Mednikova ran a battery of
tests. Concerning these remains, we we
haven't found
indications of trauma in this case.
But while none of the children's bones
were broken, their teeth show something
unexpected.
We can notice such [music]
transversal lines on the anterior teeth.
Here and [music] also here, they are
visible. That means that growth of
those children was interrupted [music]
>> [snorts]
>> by some
strong hunger, starvation.
This suggests that in the region [music]
where the children lived, game was
becoming scarce.
As hunger and desperation [music]
grew, their tribe may have appealed to a
higher power for help.
That brings us back to the thousands of
beads in the children's grave.
Researchers have determined that each
bead took at least an hour to make.
The enormous effort suggests an
extraordinary purpose.
They were decorated in special, rich
manner to send some message to another
worlds, to God.
Maria can't say how the children died,
but she believes she knows why.
Such young people, [music] they were
very important for their society because
they were just
close to the adults, and they were
hopeful scientists. They could [music]
be a gift for some gods.
So, they could be sacrificed.
Covered in beads of ivory, a boy and
girl were sent into the hereafter so
that their tribe could continue to walk
the earth.
>> [music]
>> Today, just outside the State Historical
Museum in Red Square,
Russia and Poland will meet in battle.
In this annual military band
competition, Poland and Russia vie for
top honors.
Today, their rivalry is all good fun.
But in the 17th century, Poland and
Russia were at each other's throats
in a bloody struggle for supremacy in
Eastern Europe.
>> [screaming]
>> And at the forefront of this conflict, a
warrior both dark and strange.
>> [music]
>> For nearly two centuries, Poland's
[music] winged hussars were undefeated
across the battlefields of Europe
and the most feared army in the land.
The reason why is our museum's [music]
secret.
To investigate,
we've come to the ranch of a Hussar
enthusiast and proud Polish-American,
Rick Fox.
The purpose of the wings has baffled and
divided historians for centuries.
Some believe that the wings made a
hissing sound,
and that the hissing of a thousand wings
would have terrified the enemy.
Did a frightening sound give Polish
Hussars the edge? There's lots of
legends about the wings. Some say that
they made noise. Some say they vibrated.
My wings have, on rare occasions, have
made a buzzing sound. Uh they've scared
horses that were nearby. So, you know,
we know that that to be true. I've never
actually had myself mic'd. We've never
done a a setup like this before uh to
try and see if we can replicate it.
So, I was always here. With the aid of a
sensitive sound recorder, recording now.
Rick hopes to capture any sound the
wings might make
and put the age-old debate to rest.
Okay, so we got the recorder here. I'm
going to take a listen and see what what
we got.
Couldn't really
couldn't really hear anything. Want you
to pick it up. Do you hear anything?
>> a lot of wind. Just ambient noise, wind,
flags, horse, and armor. Yeah. I can't
hear the wings. And I'm and of course
I'm sitting in front of the feathers and
I didn't hear anything today, so.
>> No.
It's unfortunate. Would have liked to
hear it.
Hate to put a pin in the romantic
balloon of of the legend, but I I
there's more going on in the on the
battlefield by real sounds of war
that are going to overshadow any sounds
that the wings may have made.
If it wasn't sound that terrified their
enemies, then what could it have been?
Rick thinks the answer lies in something
that every Hussar carried into battle.
The signature weapon of the Hussars was
the lance, in Polish called kopia. They
were hollowed out for lightness. They
were designed to impale and shatter on
impact. Then it was it's a terrifying
weapon.
While Russian infantrymen had pikes that
were 15 ft long, the Hussars lances
measured 20.
So, in a battle with a Russian
adversary, a Polish Hussar could impale
his [music] target 5 ft before his enemy
could reach it.
As lances go, the Hussars weapon was
highly effective.
But by the 17th century, both Russia and
Poland were fielding regiments of
armored musketeers.
You might think that muskets would have
stopped the Hussars in their tracks,
but they didn't.
Those weapons were not rifled. They
weren't accurate. Uh it was a ball.
Didn't always fit perfectly. Powder
consistency wasn't always right on.
Uh it was hit and miss.
Unlike the plodding Russian infantry,
the winged Hussars were lightning fast.
The Hussars would start at a walk,
then it would work their way to a trot.
The enemy would fire a salvo,
and within that moment of going from
trot to canter to gallop, Hussars would
pretty much cross the field in moments
before, you know, the the muskets could
actually hit them.
With speed, precision, and sheer force,
the Hussars easily smashed through
Russian infantry columns.
And there was one more thing that
assured their victory in battle.
To see a charge coming at you several
hundred or several thousand, the ground
shook like like an earthquake.
And through the smoke and the and the
musket the powder burning and and clouds
of gunsmoke in front of you and you
would start to see the tops of the
[music] lance pennants coming towards
you and the wings those spectacular
wings, you knew there was not going to
be too many
guys with dry pants. Because to to
receive a charge from the Hussars is is
death.
And that's why every Russian soldier
feared the angels of death of the
battlefield, the Polish winged Hussars.
It would take several [music] centuries
for conflict between Russia and Poland
to be reduced from violence on the
battlefield
to a battle of the bands.
Just outside Moscow's State Historical
Museum,
tourists pose with look-alikes from
Russia's past.
Tsar Nicholas II,
Vladimir Lenin,
and Joseph Stalin. [music]
This woman looks unafraid.
Perhaps that's because she doesn't know
that she's posing with Ivan the
Terrible.
Inside the museum, Ivan has an entire
gallery all to himself.
>> [music]
[music]
>> The case contains several books in
Ivan's own handwriting.
And above them is this.
>> [music]
>> Hair shirts were often worn by monks who
hoped to show remorse for their sins by
suffering extreme pain.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Why would Ivan the Terrible, powerful
leader and notorious tyrant, want to
wear this?
How did Ivan the Terrible become Ivan
the Remorseful?
That is our museum's secret.
The story begins in 1547
as a young Ivan is crowned the first
Tsar of Russia.
He came to power at a time when Russia's
noble class, the boyars, were agitating
for a larger share of power.
Some may have believed that Ivan would
be a pushover.
They were wrong.
The new Tsar sought to unify and
modernize his nation, protecting the
borders by creating a people's army
known as the Streltsy.
Ivan was a complicated man.
He was an avid chess
who brought careful calculation into
everything he did.
He was also deeply religious.
Like his subjects, he believed that even
the smallest sin could lead to eternal
damnation.
He felt that his subjects would be more
likely to follow him if they understood
the depth of his religious devotion.
To prove his piety, he built the church
that has become an icon of Russia
itself.
Saint Basil's Cathedral.
Ivan the Terrible believed that God was
on his side because the God, as he
believed, gives him a power to rule the
country. That was his mission.
>> [singing]
>> Believing he should answer to God alone,
Ivan proposed laws that would give him
absolute power.
The boyars resisted,
insisting that Ivan rule by consensus.
Instead of leading an army against the
boyars, Ivan made an unexpected move.
He left his palace in Moscow to take up
residence in the village of Alexandrov
Sloboda.
Historian Larisa Zaruskaia believes this
was a brilliant tactic.
Ivan knew that the boyars would realize
that they couldn't rule Russia without
him.
And soon they begged him to come back.
Ivan agreed [music] to return
on condition that the boyars accede to
his demand for absolute power.
And that he be allowed to command his
own secret police.
Ivan ordered them to identify and arrest
anyone who might pose a threat to his
rule.
His methods were ruthless and
terrifying.
And when suspected traitors wouldn't
talk,
Ivan had them brought here.
Under Ivan's direction, his secret
police extracted information and
confessions through brutality and
torture.
Victims were flayed alive and boiled in
oil.
>> [screaming]
>> Often their agony lasted for days.
Ivan's methods cemented his power,
giving him the authority to launch wars
that would expand and unify the Russian
state.
He would continue to use torture to
pursue his goals
until in the 37th year of his reign,
he began to reflect on his sins.
He feared no man,
but he did fear God. He was very
religious. He knew that he would like to
enter paradise someday, and he knew that
he was very severe, and a lot of people
were
brought into prison and were killed
according to his order. And as a
religious man, he started to be prepared
for this new afterlife.
In an attempt to [music] appease God,
Ivan ordered the creation of this,
a synodic, a Russian book of the dead.
Where did he connect
>> [music]
>> historically?
>> For each name, a prayer was to be given
to soothe the souls of those who
perished under Ivan.
>> [music]
>> And so, tormented [music] still, Ivan
turned to the garment that would make
him penitent in the eyes of God.
And legend has it that for the remainder
of his days, Ivan wore only the hair
shirt.
And that's because Ivan the Terrible had
become Ivan the Remorseful.
>> [music]
>> The newest wing of the State Historical
Museum is dedicated to Napoleon's
invasion of Russia.
Or as it's known to Russians, the
Patriotic War of 1812.
The collection celebrates one of
Russia's greatest victories and one of
Napoleon's worst defeats.
EVERY YEAR, THOUSANDS OF re-enactors
come to Russia to commemorate the Battle
of Borodino.
Napoleon's army's bloodiest day.
The reenactors pride themselves on
authenticity.
From their uniforms to their weapons to
this,
the French Imperial Eagle.
The Eagle was a sacred emblem that every
French regiment carried into battle.
French soldiers swore to defend it to
the death.
Inside the State Historical Museum is an
Imperial Eagle of the third French
regiment.
One of the few surviving examples in the
world.
But this Eagle should not be here. The
reason why is a museum secret.
The secret has brought Victor Eiser to
Russia from his home in Canada.
Victor is the president of a
Montreal-based reenactment group called
the Guard Napoleon.
He's here as a member of the Imperial
Guard, but he's also a soldier of the
third regiment.
That gives him a special interest in the
museum's Eagle.
The Eagle represents our regiment and
has our number on it. We follow it. And
even in a reenactment, when we have a
mock battle,
the Eagle is protected. If you lost your
Eagle, it was a terrible disgrace.
The interesting thing about reenactors,
when we don the uniforms, we feel
younger and and we [music] feel
passionate. We're proud of our regiment.
So, just as the Eagle was life and death
to the regiments 200 years ago, [music]
we feel very much the same way. So, when
I heard that there was an Eagle in
Moscow, I was interested. But when it
was described as third of the line,
[music]
I suddenly questioned how that could be.
As far as we know, we never lost an
Eagle in battle.
The third French infantry was one of the
most illustrious regiments in Napoleon's
army.
Its soldiers were often bloodied, but
never defeated.
And according [music] to the regiment's
records, they never left an eagle
behind.
The possibility to go and see the eagle
with my own eyes and try and resolve the
discrepancy between the history I know
and whatever background history they
have on their eagle is essential. I
can't go home without that.
Victor's next stop, the 1812 Gallery.
He's going to examine the museum's eagle
with the help of curator Dmitri Puzakov.
So, here is [music] the famous eagle.
This
eagle of the third regiment of the line.
This is what I've come so far to see.
I I've noticed this button with the
number three, so it makes that eagle of
your regiment. Well, certainly my heart
is pounding, and that's why for me it's
of course emotionally looking at it and
saying
I know my regimental history says we
didn't lose it. And then when you see
it, then you go
I don't know. Some some mystery is
there.
Victor [music] needs to take a closer
look.
Because the eagle is too precious to be
removed from its case,
Victor and Dmitri take some
high-definition photographs.
They hope to capture details [music]
that are invisible to the naked eye.
On a computer monitor, they examine the
image in a magnified view.
Maybe on the close-ups we can There we
go. Yeah.
At this point, the two men make a
surprising discovery.
There was something [music] that was
then scratched scratched off.
With the lighting?
>> You can really see that there's It's
five.
And I think that's definitely a one.
One. It's the the definitely not
authentic a number.
The men are stunned.
The original number was not three, but
15.
Dmitry suspects that someone assembled
the eagle and its number
from available parts. And my guess would
be that they had [music] an eagle with a
damaged number for 15. And they they had
an authentic number three and put it on
the base of of the eagle to make it look
more authentic [music] than the with the
broken numbers.
Yeah. Victor knows that there were
several Napoleonic regiments with the
number 15.
One 15th regiment served in Russia
and was decimated during Napoleon's
final defeat at Waterloo.
But when the regiment was disbanded, its
eagle was destroyed.
There is no record that any 15th
regiment ever lost its eagle.
Victor and Dmitry have solved one
mystery
only to reveal another. I'm much
relieved that it's not my regiment that
lost its eagle, but still to be able to
see
200 years of history
there
uh
is very moving.
If I was someone from the 15th who
happened to be touring through, I'd like
to know where it came from, how it got
there. But with the few eagles still
existing [music] in the world, they now
represent all the French armies that
fought during that period. [music] So,
today it really doesn't matter whether
it's the third or the 15th, whatever.
The respect that the men held for it,
that the men died for it, followed it is
still there.
So, it's no less valuable. And anyone
[music] seeing the eagle should be proud
of that
type of heroic determination.
Moscow's State Historical Museum makes
no secret of the opulent lifestyle of
the Tsars.
Over the centuries that they ruled, the
Tsars acquired [music] enormous wealth.
But all this ended with the Communist
Revolution
of 1917. [music]
After the execution of Tsar Nicholas,
the culture of excess was replaced by
the classless equality of the Soviet
state.
And that makes one of the museum's
acquisitions a little strange.
It's the only artifact with fog lamps
and an all-leather interior.
It's a Rolls-Royce car,
>> [music]
>> Silver Ghost model.
This luxury vehicle was owned by
Communist leader Vladimir Lenin. Lenin
used [music] this car for traveling
around Moscow,
to the suburbs of Moscow, in the
surroundings.
Of course, it was a very convenient for
Lenin, I think, to make speeches and to
have some discussions, maybe with people
who gathered around the cars in the Red
Square or in the streets of Moscow.
Lenin declared that revolutionaries must
guard against bourgeois tendencies.
>> [groaning]
>> So, why did Lenin own a Rolls?
That's our museum secret.
The investigation begins at Moscow's
premier Rolls-Royce showroom.
Until the fall of the Soviet Union,
there were no dealerships in Russia.
But perhaps a visiting salesperson
convinced Lenin that the Rolls was his
kind of car.
People who buy Rolls-Royces are
definitely very successful people. So
far, so good. Lenin was definitely a
successful revolutionary.
And they don't want any [music]
compromises. That sounds like Lenin,
too.
When counter-revolutionaries challenged
him, he started a bloody civil war.
Definitely not a compromiser.
Of course, these people [music] can
afford to buy the best.
That part doesn't sound like Lenin. He
wasn't a rich man.
But early on in the revolution, his
Bolsheviks had liberated the Tsar's gold
and the Tsar's collection of fine
automobiles.
There were about 40 motorcars in the
Tsar's garage. And it seems that even
the communist leaders were not against
such cars.
So perhaps Lenin owned this Rolls
because he got it for free.
To be certain, we'll need to prove that
Tsar Nicholas was the original owner.
Unfortunately, we haven't got the
original documents.
But we will speak about our car and
about its identity. We have got the
chassis number and the chassis number is
fixed to the front of the dashboard
under the [music] bonnet.
17 kg is clearly visible.
But with a car this old, it would be
surprising [music]
if the chassis number could be traced.
Or maybe not.
Rolls-Royce keeps [music] records on all
the cars of previous years to track
those cars that have [music] wonderful
history behind them.
Incredibly, a request to head office
elicits the original bill of sale.
The purchaser was not Tsar Nicholas,
but an emissary of Vladimir Lenin.
The date is 1922.
In the years following the bloody
revolution, all industrial nations
imposed an embargo forbidding trade with
the Russian communist state.
So, how did Lenin manage to do business
with a British car maker?
A clue lies not in cars,
but planes.
Rolls-Royce made the best engines for
bomber planes, and Lenin needed them for
his war machine.
Lenin asked the British to break the
embargo.
He knew that Britain was mired in
depression
with idle factories and hungry workers.
British leaders held their noses and
allowed Lenin to buy several of their
most advanced [music] airplane engines.
To sweeten the deal, Lenin was given a
15% discount on something else.
A Rolls-Royce automobile.
The Rolls-Royce plane engines helped
Lenin and his Bolsheviks win the civil
war and impose a brutal totalitarian
state.
But the question remains, should he have
kept the car?
Of course not.
Lenin was our leader of a communist
party, and the motto of that party was
that all people have to be equal. He
should have done something that the
whole country is driving Rolls-Royces.
>> [laughter]
>> In this place where power and piety
meet,
for every mystery we reveal, far more
must remain unspoken.
Secrets of sacrifice
and strategy.
Hidden in plain sight
inside Moscow's State Historical Museum.
>> [music]